原视频名：Tango Delta - Perseverance Begins Life On Mars
原作者名：Scott Manley
视频来源：youtu.be/zvvzvXb2Awc
原视频发布日期：20210220
字幕翻译/压制：旋火
Hello it's Scott Manley here.
你好 我是Scott Manley
By now you have probably all heard that the Mars rover Perseverance has successfully landed on Mars.
现在你们可能都听说了毅力号漫游车已经成功着陆火星
Yes that is a great relief
是的 这让人如释重负
because this is the second time that we've tried the very Kerbal sky crane mechanic
因为这是我们第二次尝试非常坎巴拉的天空起重机这样的方式了
and yeah it has worked successfully to place a vehicle on the surface and much more on target
是的 它已经成功地将航天器放置在了地面上 而且更准
because this time it had an active navigation system which we'll what we can talk about.
因为这次它有一个主动导航系统 我们待会来谈谈它
But yeah I haven't been able to make a video about this
但是 是的 我还没有能够做一个关于这个视频
because well firstly I've been very busy with my day job and getting kids to scout camp and stuff
因为首先我一直忙于我的日常工作 以及让孩子们参加童子军夏令营之类的事情
but also just they haven't released very many pictures.
但也只是因为 他们还没有发布 很多的图片
I mean we understood that straight after landing
我是指 在刚着陆后不久
they would get a couple of images as quickly as possible.
他们会尽快得到几张图片
During the landing they don't really have a good direct line of sight
在着陆过程中 下降级和地球并没有一个很好的直线连接
so they would be relaying data via the Mars Reconnaissance Orbiter right.
那么他们会通过火星侦察轨道器(MRO)来转发数据对吧
They would have satellites in orbit
有卫星在轨道上
and these would be taking data from the low-gain antenna and relaying that to Earth.
通过低增益天线获取数据 并将其转发到地球
It's called bent pipe telemetry.
这就是所谓的弯管遥测
And these have a limited time when they're above the horizon.
在火星处在(地球)地平线以上的时间是有限的
In that time they delivered two and a quarter images.
在这段时间里 又传送了2.25张图像
We got a thumbnail from the forward Hazcam and the rear Hazcam
我们从前方和后方的避障相机得到了缩略图
and the quarter of an improper image downloaded and that was it.
还有四分之一张照片 那是没下完的 就这些
These images were very small, black and white.
这些图片都是非常小的 黑白的
So you didn't really get to see much
所以 你没有真的看到很多
but you got to see enough to show that the vehicle was on the ground.
但已经足够得知毅力号已经着陆到了火星表面
You could make out some terrain in the distance.
你可以看到远处的一些地形
Some rocks very close by
以及一些非常接近的岩石
and of course the framing of the covers that were there to protect it
当然 还有保护它的盖子的框架
because during landing even under rockets that are way above you
因为在着陆过程中 即使是在比你高得多的火箭下面
there's a lot of debris going around.
周围还是有很多碎片
So anyway we have confirmed touchdown.
那么无论如何 我们已经确认着陆
There was a press conference to talk about
有一场新闻发布会 谈论道
how they're all happy that everything's down and to expect more data soon.
他们都很高兴 所有数据都下载下来 并期待很快就有更多的数据
And the next day we get a nice little press conference with like a handful of images.
而在第二天 进行了一场漂亮的小型新闻发布会 以及少量的图像
I think I can currently count the number of images we've got from this spacecraft on the fingers of hands.
我想我现在可以用手指头来数我们从这个航天器上得到的图像数量
But we will expect more.
但我们会期待到更多的图像
So we have a color image from the front hazard cameras.
那么我们得到了前部避障相机拍下的彩色照片
In one case you get to see a really nice close-up of the wheel sitting on the surface.
在其中一张照片中 你可以看到一个非常漂亮的特写镜头 其中轮子踩在火星表面上
You can see some rocks in there with little pits on them.
你可以看到一些有着小坑的岩石
Not sure whether those are like volcanic rocks or the vesicles have been eroded or anything
不知道这些是火山岩还是被侵蚀的小坑还是其他的东西
but most importantly though we got an amazing image from the descent down look camera
但最重要的是 从下降级往下拍的相机的图像是很惊人的
showing the rover hanging meters above the surface of Mars
显示出漫游车悬挂在距离火星表面数米高的地方
as the sky crane is slowly descending to a touchdown.
而天空起重机正缓缓下降 准备着陆
So this is an amazing image.
那么这是一个惊人的图像
And it's actually only going to be one image from a much longer movie.
而且这实际上只是一部长得多的视频中的一个画面
So it's great because it's only a couple of meters above the surface.
那么这很好 因为它离火星表面只有几米高
You can see the dust getting thrown around and blown around.
你可以看到尘埃被吹来吹去
And you can also see the cables coming up that are supporting it.
你还可以看到支撑它的缆绳
Now there's four cables in this image.
那么这张图里有四条缆绳
Three of them are load-bearing cables from the bridle.
其中三条是框架上的承重缆绳
The fourth is a data cable which is of course sending the data from the sky crane down into the rover
第四条是数据线 当然是把数据从天空起重机传到漫游车上
because it's where the cameras are right.
因为天空起重机上有相机对吧
There's multiple cameras on the sky crane stage
天空起重机的分级上面有好几台相机
and that's going down into it.
而数据就要向下传给漫游车
Now if you were listening to the JPL Raw stream
那么 如果你在听JPL Raw频道的直播流(音频)
that's where you got to hear the mission controllers and everyone talking and describing the descent.
就会听到的任务控制员 以及每个人都在谈论和描述的下降过程
that was that was by far the best stream.
那是迄今为止最好的直播
I know there was a great public stream by NASA.
我知道NASA也搞了一个面向公众的很好的直播流
They had a lot of people talking about how they were inspired by space missions and stuff like that
他们有很多人在谈论他们是如何受到太空任务和类似的东西的启发的
whereas over in the JPL stream they were talking about numbers telemetry and reading out the numbers
而在JPL的直播中 他们在谈论遥测数字和读出数字的事情
and there was a great deal of excitement when we heard the phrase tango delta, touched down.
而当我们听到探戈德尔塔 着陆这句话的时候 也是非常的兴奋的
But yeah I should clarify
但是 是的 我应该澄清
I heard that and I was like yes we're there.
我听到这句话 我就想是的 我们到了
But that isn't really the case because that's the equivalent of Neil Armstrong or Buzz Aldrin saying contact light.
但事实并非如此 因为这相当于尼尔·阿姆斯特朗或巴兹·奥尔德林说的接触灯亮
That was tango delta is a sort of internal phrase to say
而探戈德尔塔 是一种内部用语 用来表示
we've got rover wheels on the surface of Mars but we haven't properly landed yet
漫游车的轮子接触到了火星表面 但还没有正式着陆
because from that point they still had to confirm that was stable on the surface.
因为从那时候起 他们还必须确认漫游车已经稳稳地处在了火星表面
then cut the cables they had to cut the bridle cables
然后切断缆绳 特别是承重缆绳
and then a couple of seconds later they would cut the data cable in the sky crane would fly off.
然后几秒钟后 他们就会切断天空起重机的数据线 再飞走
So that was when the proper touchdown happens
那么这才是正式的着陆进行的时候
when the the Mars rover stopped wobbling and the sky crane had achieved a safe distance.
当漫游车停止摇晃 天空起重机达到安全距离时
That was when they actually called the landing just for those that are interested.
这时他们才宣布着陆 说这些就是为了让那些对此感兴趣的人知道这是怎么回事
So yeah we are currently waiting for a lot of images to come down.
所以 是的 我们目前正在等待大量的图像下载下来
From the multitude of engineering cameras which are going to be were used during the descent.
也就是众多的下降段使用的工程相机中拍到的图像
These are engineering cameras which many people compared to GoPros
这些都是工程相机 很多人把它比作GoPro
but technically they are FLIR. FLIR's like a Forward-Looking InfraRed
但在技术上 它们是FLIR FLIR全称前视红外仪
and this is a company that makes machine, video solutions for infrared and invisible wavelength.
而这是一家做机械和红外以及非可见光波段相机解决方案的公司
And these are machine vision cameras for industrial automation.
而这些都是工业自动化的机器视觉相机
So they're pretty small.
所以是相当小的
They're very similar to GoPros
和GoPro非常相似
They're just designed for industrial environments.
但只是为工业环境设计的
They have maybe actually have more than four
他们也许实际上有超过四个这样的相机
but there are four directions that these things point.
但指向四个方向
We have a bunch looking upwards at the parachute being deployed.
有一些相机向上拍到了正在部署中的降落伞
That's on the descent stage.
那是在下降级上的相机
There's a number that are on the descent stage looking down at the rover.
有一些是在下降级向下拍漫游车
Some on the rover looking up at the descent stage
有一些则在漫游车上向上拍下降级
and a bunch on the rover looking down at the ground coming up
还有一堆在漫游车上俯视即将出现的火星表面
and between all of these during the descent we are expecting 28 000 images or thereabouts.
而在下降过程中 所有这些相机预计会产生28000张左右的图像
And you know all these engineering cameras aren't just for pretty pictures.
而你知道 所有的这些工程相机不只是为了拍漂亮的照片
I mean they're there to actually do a little bit of science
我是指 它们实际上是可以用来做一点科学工作的
but they're really there for the engineers are trying to solve the problems of landing on Mars.
但它们真正的作用是让工程师们解决着陆火星的问题
That's why there are cameras that are pointing at the parachute to watch how it deploys at supersonic speeds.
这就是为什么有相机对准降落伞 观察它在超音速下如何展开的
And perhaps more importantly the cameras looking downwards
也许更重要的是那些向下拍的相机
will show the interaction of the rocket plumes with the surface of Mars
会显示出火箭排出的羽流与火星表面的相互作用
because if you are trying to land something much bigger say a Starship on the surface of Mars
因为如果你想把更大的东西降落在火星表面 比如说一艘Starship
you want to make sure that you're not going to throw debris everywhere and make the vehicle unable to land
你就要确保你不会把碎片吹得到处都是 使航天器无法降落
like destroying the land that you're trying to land on as you're trying to land on it.
也就是把即将着陆的位置摧毁
I think it's monday before we actually get to see that
我觉得到了周一(当地时间2月22日)就差不多能看到了
and maybe what we see on monday is just the thumbnail versions.
也许我们在周一看到的只是缩略图的版本
We're not really getting the view into this program that we would like to.
我们并没有像我们预想的那样真正了解到这个项目
In fact I've seen people complaining about how slow these releases are happening.
事实上 我已经看到人们在抱怨这些发布的速度有多慢
The official raw data download site still only has 2.25 images despite other images having been released.
官方的原始数据下载网站仍然只有2.25张图片 尽管其他图片已经发布
but these are not the raw images by the looks of things.
但从外观上来看 这些发布出去的都不是原始图像
We also got a fabulous image from the Mars Reconnaissance Orbiter
我们还从MRO上获得了一张美妙的图像
which not only was it providing a relay for the telemetry,
而MRO不仅是为遥测提供中继
it was also taking an image and it showed the vehicle under the parachute towards landing.
还拍摄一张照片 显示了正在使用降落伞降落的航天器
We've only seen like a low quality jpeg version.
我们只看到了一个低质量的jpeg版本
The full quality version hasn't yet been released
完整质量的版本还没有被发布出来
so I'm hoping when that happens
所以我希望到时候
we'll be able to actually see things like the heat shield falling away and other data.
我们将能够看到诸如隔热板分离等数据
I'm really looking forward to this.
我真的很期待这个
Let's be clear.
让我先说清楚
Yeah. This is something that's very exciting but it's very hard to talk about it
是啊 这是非常令人兴奋的事情 但很难讨论它
because we don't really have that much data.
因为我们真的没有那么多数据
As of right now yeah they're going through their post landing checklist.
就目前而言 是的 他们正在进行着陆后的检查
I think about now they should be starting to think about folding up the Mastcam
我想现在他们应该开始考虑展开桅杆相机了
so the Mast has most of the major science cameras on it
那么桅杆上有大多数主要的科学相机
so the images have been released so far have been things like navigation cameras or hazard avoidance cameras.
那么到目前为止 导航相机和避障相机的照片已经发布了
These are low slung ones kind of like backup cameras as some people described.
这些相机都有些太靠近地面了 或者像备份相机 如某些人说的那样
And they're down very near the ground and they're in pairs
它们非常靠近地面 而且成双成对
so they can actually provide high quality images of rocks
因此 他们可以真正提供高质量的岩石图像
and they can make sure that they're not about to drive into something
同时确保不会开车撞到什么东西
when they're driving under like autonomous mode.
也就是在自主模式下驾驶时
They're front Hazcams and the rear Hazcams although I like to call those ass cams
分为前避障相机和后避障相机 尽管我喜欢叫这些后避障相机为屁股相机
and on the Mast that's where you have the real science cameras
而在桅杆上有真正的科学相机
and the science cameras are very different.
而科学相机有很大的不同
These are the ones that have multiple filters in place.
这些科学相机都有多个滤光片
They do all the science.
负责所有的科学工作
So yeah I think there's like 23 cameras in total on the entire vehicle.
所以 我觉得整个航天器上一共有23台相机
Bunch of them are discarded by the descent stage.
其中一部分在下降级上被丢弃了
There's one that is on the rover which is used for the landing navigation
漫游车上有一个相机是用于着陆导航的
where they pick the landing site and diverted towards it.
也就是选择着陆点 并向它飞去
That's essentially useless now because it's designed to focus at a distance
现在基本上没有用了 因为它的设计是为了在远处对焦
and now it's like inches from the ground so it can't work.
现在它距离地面很近 所以不能工作
By the way I saw a bunch of people during the descent or after the landing
顺便说一下 我看到一堆人说 在下降过程中或者说在降落后
there was a report that they were 35 meters from near as boulder they can identify from orbit
有报告说 距离最近的可以从轨道上观测到的巨石只有35米远
and a lot of people took that to mean
很多人认为这意味着
Wow they managed to land within 35 meters of their target.
哇 他们成功地降落在目标的35米内
That's not actually what they're saying there.
他们说的实际上并不是这个意思
What they're saying is the autonomous navigation
他们说的是自主导航
put them no closer than 35 meters to a hazard that they could identify from orbit.
让他们距离轨道上可以看到的危险不超过35米的距离内着陆
The descent system what it did was it took the photo of the area figured out where it was in the map
下降系统所做的是拍下该地区的照片并找出它在地图上的位置
and then they had a predefined map that said these areas are red.
然后他们有一个预定义的地图 说这些地区是红色的
Do not land here.
不要降落在这里
These areas are green.
这些地区是绿色的
Land here.
降落在这里
And that's what it did.
这就是它所做的
So 35 meters is actually the bigger that is the better it is.
所以35米这个数值实际上是越大越好
It seems that they're landed in a pretty good place.
他们似乎是降落在一个很好的地方
The geologists will tell you they're excited.
地质学家会告诉你他们对此很兴奋
I'm honestly not enough of a geologist to know where the least interesting place to land on Mars would be.
老实说 在地质学方面我还不够格 不知道在火星上着陆 哪些地方会是最无聊的
I suspect the least interesting place would be on top of another spacecraft.
我猜测最无聊的地方应该是在另一个航天器的顶部
That would be kind of catastrophic I don't know how that would happen.
这将是灾难性的 我不知道这会怎么发生
But hopefully if all goes according to plan
但希望如果一切都按计划进行的话
there will be another spacecraft trying to land in this region in the coming years
未来几年将有另一个航天器试图在该地区着陆
because this is a precursor mission for sample return.
因为毅力号是样本返回的前驱任务
And it's going to be taking samples putting them in little test tubes and caching them on the surface
它将会采集样本 放在小试管里 然后缓存到表面
and then years later we're going to have a rover come along pick these up load them on to another spacecraft
几年后 会有另一个漫游车走过来 把这些东西装到另一个航天器上
which will carry them to another spacecraft in orbit
再把样品送到轨道上的另一个航天器上
which will carry them home.
再带回家
This is going to be a decade worth of science at least.
这个科学成果至少值十年
But right now they're just in post landing operations.
但现在他们只是在进行着陆后的操作
They are checking out their stuff.
他们正在检查他们的东西
They've folded Mast up probably about now.
他们大概现在已经把桅杆展开了
They'll be folding up the antenna figuring out where they are, figuring out how to point that.
他们会把天线展开 弄清楚自己在哪儿 然后要指向哪里
They will be switching over the software
他们将切换软件
because the rover came down
因为漫游车在下降过程中
and it would be running the software that was needed for the descent and landing.
要运行下降和着陆所需的软件
Now it's there they can delete all those files from memory
现在它已经着陆了 就可以从存储中删除所有这些文件
and switch over to the ground operations only.
并转而只负责地面的操作
So that'll be over the coming few days.
所以 这将是在未来几天会做的事情
They've successfully talked to the Ingenuity or Ginny this helicopter
他们已经成功地与机智号或者说吉尼号直升机进行了沟通
so that's technically a separate spacecraft.
所以从技术上讲 这是一个独立的航天器
It's currently connected by a cable that's how it's getting all its charging.
目前它是通过一条电缆连接的 它就是这样进行充电的
But they can talk to that separately and make sure that it's healthy.
但他们可以与之单独联系 并确保它的健康
I believe we're talking over a month before this actually gets to position where it will be able to fly.
我觉得距离它的飞行还得有一个月的时间
And yeah looking forward to that a whole lot.
是的 我对此有很多的期待
They say it could fly up to four times.
他们说 它可以飞四次
I'm hoping that they get some sort of mission extension there
我希望他们能得到某种延长任务
because this thing is far too cool.
因为这东西太酷了
Yeah so that's the state of things.
是啊 所以这些就是一些事情的状态
I'm sorry I don't have any fancy insights or anything for you.
对不起 我没有任何花哨的见解
There was one cool.
有一件事很酷
Somebody from JPL tweeted an image of their desktop showing the range control phase of the flight.
某个JPL的人在推特上发了一张他们桌面的图片 显示了飞行的范围控制阶段
And I initially mistook the angle for the range control as the lander trying to traverse towards the surface
我一开始误以为范围控制的角度 也就是着陆器试图向火星表面移动的角度
but this is actually during the hypersonic descent on with the heat shield.
但这实际上这是在高超音速下降过程中 在有隔热板的情况下
The vehicle is forced to turn, right.
航天器被迫的转动 对吧
It has an offset center of mass that causes the vehicle to turn one way or another.
它有一个偏移的质量中心 导致飞行器得转向一个方向或另一个方向
And so it does these roll reversals, weaving its way towards the target that it wants
所以它做了这些滚转的动作 朝着它想要的目标蜿蜒前进
and if it realizes the target is further away than it expects it can roll (upwards) so that it gets a bit of lift
如果它意识到目标比预期的要远 它就可以向上翻转 这样就能得到一定的升力
and if it's going to be closer than it expects it can roll downwards to drive it down
如果目标比预期的更近 它可以向下翻转 以俯冲
and if it just is at the right distance it can weave left and right to try to put itself there.
如果距离合适 可以左右迂回
So that's what these 60 degree angles I was remarking on are talking about.
那么这就是我所说的60度角
So yeah I'm not sure what else there is to talk about but hopefully we'll see more on monday.
那么是的 我不知道还有什么可以谈的 但希望我们在周一会看到更多的东西
Until then I'm Scott Manley. Fly safe.
在那之前 我是Scott Manley 切记 注意飞行安全
[Music]
[音乐]